<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-27T12:44:25+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes of Chap17 Lithium ion secondary cells(Linden’s Handbook of Batteries)</title><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes of Chap17 Lithium ion secondary cells(Linden’s Handbook of Batteries)"/><published>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence/"><![CDATA[<p>lol</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="battery-study"/><category term="batteries"/><category term="lithium-ion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My first blog]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build a equivalent circuit of batteries from scratch</title><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build a equivalent circuit of batteries from scratch"/><published>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog is a summary of the problems and concerns one may encounter when consider the battery system. Detailed formulas are not included just a general description.</p> <p>Some notes and insights from <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Battery-Management-Systems-Modeling-Engineering/dp/1630810231">L.Plett’s book</a><br/> Also from the lecture notes of C26, used without permission but I did cite something.</p> <h2 id="open-circuit-voltageocv-and-state-of-chargesoc-dependence">Open circuit voltage(OCV) and State of Charge(SOC) dependence</h2> <p>The first thing one thinks to build a equivalent circuit is to ADD a <em>voltage source</em> to the circuit. From high school physics, the <em>open circuit voltage</em> is supposed to be the voltage at infinite large load, which means the current density is approximately zero. I previously thinks that the OCV may related to current density, diffusion, kinetics. However, I misunderstood the concept of OCV it is not working. Ideally there is no current, consequently no diffusion and kinetics problems. It should be more stable then I had thought.</p> <p>Nonetheless, it is by no means stationary. From Nernst equation:</p> <p>\(\Delta G = -zFE\) \(E = E^\circ - \frac{RT}{zF}ln(Q_r)\)</p> <p>with the ongoing of reaction the activity is also changed. OK, one may argue that in a <s> rockin' roll </s> the <em>rocking chair battery(RCB)</em> the solvent concentration may not change, just like their famous relative of RCB: <em>Lithium-ion batteries(LIBs)</em>. However, I still thinks SEI formation, surface reshaping, and other side effects may drive the OCV away when using the battery. So here we introduce an important concept called <em>State of Charge(SOC)</em>. This should actually mean the charge status, like SOC = 100% means fully charged. Just like the worrying battery percentage thing in your cellphone. OK, I have to admit this really confused me for several days when I first get to know the concept, because nobody told me the UNIT of SOC(unit of 1). I find people directly use the voltage in a capacitor to be the SOC and this works because ideal capacitors have a linear relationship between voltage and remaining charges.</p> <p><strong>In summary: the circuit we build now is composed of a SOC dependent voltage source.</strong></p> <p>By the way, one may come up with the question: <strong>How to test the SOC and OCV relationships?</strong>. Naturally, we may think of a simple method that we charge/discharge the battery to different SOC and wait it to reach equilibrium. This technique is called <em>Galvanostatic internmittent titration test(GITT)</em>. The method involves a small charge/discharge and then a long rest period to allow the cell to equilibrate. Then the voltages at the end of the periods are taken as the OCV. <d-cite key="C26_2"></d-cite></p> <hr/> <h2 id="small-talks">Small talks</h2> <blockquote> <p>At winter, the electric car can be driven for less distance not only because the inner resitance of bateries become larger, but also because there is 7% larger air resistance at 5 C compared with 25 C. —My kindly lecturer of C26</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="battery-study"/><category term="batteries"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First blog!]]></summary></entry></feed>