<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-27T18:26:43+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hysteresis voltage modeling</title><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Hysteresis-voltage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hysteresis voltage modeling"/><published>2024-04-27T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-27T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Hysteresis-voltage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Hysteresis-voltage/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hysteresis-voltage">Hysteresis voltage</h2> <p>Definition: OCV-SOC curves for charging and discharging Li-ion batteries do not overlap. The difference between the curves is defined as <em>Hysteresis voltage</em>.</p> <p>The modeling can be physics-based or phenomenon-based.</p> <p>I find the modeling of hysteresis is a deep field because the hysteresis phenomenon can happen in various disciplines. There is even a book about hysteresis modeling<d-cite key="hysteresismodelingmath"></d-cite>. There are plenty of different models to model a hysteresis, such as Prandtl-Ishlinskii hysteresis model<d-cite key="4739202"></d-cite>. However, they are not covered in this blog post. I just put them here for further reference. The main framework is still from L. Plett’s book.<d-cite key="BMS_vol1"></d-cite></p> <h2 id="main-circle-and-minor-circle">Main circle and minor circle</h2> <p>This part is mainly from the Guillaume Larrat’s thesis. <d-cite key="Lihysteresismodeling"></d-cite></p> <p>The charging and discharging OCV curves that were displayed in the figure below allows to create a voltage hysteresis loop for a SOC varying from 0% to 100% which includes the whole range of possible values for the SOC.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/OCV_curve-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/OCV_curve-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/OCV_curve-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/OCV_curve.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>It is composed of the two <strong>major</strong> OCV curves: a charge from 0% to 100% SOC and a full discharge from 100% to 0%. The corresponding voltage hysteresis loop is then called a major loop. However, if the cell is partially charged or discharged from a state different than 0% or 100%, the OCV will not follow the two curves displayed earlier. If a cell is at a 60% SOC and is then discharged to 40% and then charged back to 60%, this will create a minor loop as shown in Figure below:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/major_minor_loop-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/major_minor_loop-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/major_minor_loop-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-04-27-Hysteresis-voltage/major_minor_loop.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Assupmtion: The loop of a real-time charge/discharge process only locates insides the major loop. Apparently, the changing rate in a minor loop is different from the major loop.</p> <h2 id="the-model">The model</h2> <p>Let’s just build a simple model:<br/> Assumptions:</p> <ul> <li>Linear: The changing rate of hysteresis voltage only depends the difference between maxium OCV and current OCV.</li> <li>Past invariant: The hyseresis does not depend on the using history but just state. Actually, this is not true.</li> </ul> \[\frac{dh(z,t)}{dz} = \gamma sgn(\dot z)(M(z,\dot z)- h(z,t))\] <p>$M(z,\dot z)$: A function that gives the maximum polarization due to the</p> <h2 id="afterwords">Afterwords</h2> <p>I did not heard about this topic too much before when I concentrated at ElectroChemistry. The hysteresis effect is important for Battery Management Systems.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="battery-study"/><category term="batteries"/><category term="lithium-ion"/><category term="battery-study"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduce hysteresis voltage and its modeling]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Warburg impedence</title><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warburg impedence"/><published>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/Warburg-impedence/"><![CDATA[<p>The most important thing is that the <em>Warburg impedence</em> models the diffusion in electrode.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="battery-study"/><category term="batteries"/><category term="lithium-ion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My first blog]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build an equivalent circuit of batteries from scratch</title><link href="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build an equivalent circuit of batteries from scratch"/><published>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-26T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://toflamus.github.io/blog/2024/equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog is a summary of the problems and concerns one may encounter when consider the battery system. Detailed formulas are not included just a general description.</p> <h2 id="open-circuit-voltageocv-and-state-of-chargesoc-dependence-">Open circuit voltage(OCV) and State of Charge(SOC) dependence <d-cite key="BMS_vol1"></d-cite></h2> <p>The first thing one thinks to build a equivalent circuit is to ADD a <em>voltage source</em> to the circuit. From high school physics, the <em>open circuit voltage</em> is supposed to be the voltage at infinite large load, which means the current density is approximately zero. I previously thinks that the OCV may related to current density, diffusion, kinetics. However, I misunderstood the concept of OCV it is not working. Ideally there is no current, consequently no diffusion and kinetics problems. It should be more stable then I had thought.</p> <p>Nonetheless, it is by no means stationary. From Nernst equation:</p> <p>\(\Delta G = -zFE\) \(E = E^\circ - \frac{RT}{zF}ln(Q_r)\)</p> <p>with the ongoing of reaction the activity is also changed. OK, one may argue that in a <s> rockin' roll </s> the <em>rocking chair battery(RCB)</em> the solvent concentration may not change, just like their famous relative of RCB: <em>Lithium-ion batteries(LIBs)</em>. However, I still thinks SEI formation, surface reshaping, and other side effects may drive the OCV away when using the battery. So here we introduce an important concept called <em>State of Charge(SOC)</em>. This should actually mean the charge status, like SOC = 100% means fully charged. Just like the worrying battery percentage thing in your cellphone. OK, I have to admit this really confused me for several days when I first get to know the concept, because nobody told me the UNIT of SOC(unit of 1). I find people directly use the voltage in a capacitor to be the SOC and this works because ideal capacitors have a linear relationship between voltage and remaining charges.</p> <p>So now we have a circuit with a SOV dependent OCV.</p> <p>By the way, one may come up with the question: <strong>How to test the SOC and OCV relationships?</strong>. Naturally, we may think of a simple method that we charge/discharge the battery to different SOC and wait it to reach equilibrium. This technique is called <em>Galvanostatic internmittent titration test(GITT)</em>. The method involves a small charge/discharge and then a long rest period to allow the cell to equilibrate. Then the voltages at the end of the periods are taken as the OCV. <d-cite key="C26_2"></d-cite></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-04-26-equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/GITT-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-04-26-equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/GITT-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-04-26-equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/GITT-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-04-26-equivalent-circuit-of-batteries/GITT.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Here is an typical graphic example of GITT<d-cite key="LIBOCVmodel"></d-cite> </div> <p>Now we can model the SOC(denoted by $z(t)$) with continuous and discrete form by differential and difference equations. Assuming that discharge current is positive.</p> <ul> <li>Continuous form: <ul> <li>$\dot z(t) = -\eta(t)i(t)/Q$</li> <li>$z(t) =z(0) -\frac{1}{Q} \int_0^t \eta(\tau)i(\tau)$</li> </ul> </li> <li>Discrete form: <ul> <li>$z[k+1] = z[k] - \frac{\Delta t}{Q}\eta[k]i[k]$</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Some other concepts and their definitions:</p> <ul> <li><em>total charge capacity(total capacity) $Q$</em>: total charge removed from SOC = 100% to SOC = 0%</li> <li><em>discharge capacity</em>: total charge removed from SOC = 100% to some cut off voltage where SOC &gt; 0%.</li> <li><em>depth of discharge(DOD)</em>: $DOD = 1 - SOC$</li> </ul> <p>OK now I am gonna say that what has been built above is straight forward but a lot too simple.There are a lot of things to be taken into account. <em>Randles circuit</em>, <em>Warburg impedence</em></p> <p>##</p> <hr/> <h2 id="small-talks">Small talks</h2> <blockquote> <p>At winter, the electric car can be driven for less distance not only because the inner resitance of bateries become larger, but also because there is 7% larger air resistance at 5 C compared with 25 C. —My kindly lecturer of C26</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="battery-study"/><category term="batteries"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First blog!]]></summary></entry></feed>